<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Middle Way Musings</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/</link><description>Recent content on Middle Way Musings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 16:00:49 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://middlewaymusings.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>There Are No Mahayana Monasteries</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/there-are-no-mahayana-monasteries/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 16:00:49 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/there-are-no-mahayana-monasteries/</guid><description>Photo by Raju Kumar on Unsplash
Introduction It has become all too common these days to refer to Buddhist monasteries (by which I mean established communities of monks or nuns that maintain traditional Vinaya observance) by their cultural flair or the doctrinal views they follow. We may call some monasteries &amp;ldquo;Tibetan&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;Zen&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Theravāda&amp;rdquo;, or even &amp;ldquo;Mahāyāna&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Hīnayāna&amp;rdquo; (i.e. Śrāvakayāna). While it may seem to make sense, these labels create unnecessary barriers between monastics who are actually much closer spiritual siblings than it may appear.</description></item><item><title>Is the Big Bang Theory Wrong?</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/is-the-big-bang-theory-wrong/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 11:33:18 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/is-the-big-bang-theory-wrong/</guid><description>Photo by James Webb Telescope
In recent years, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has unveiled discoveries that have shaken the foundations of our cosmic understanding. Among its most startling findings are fully formed, massive galaxies dating back to just 300-500 million years after the supposed Big Bang—galaxies that, according to conventional Big Bang cosmology, simply shouldn&amp;rsquo;t exist yet. These ancient galaxies appear too large, too mature, and too numerous for the standard timeline of cosmic evolution.</description></item><item><title>Does God Exist?</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/does-god-exist/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2024 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/does-god-exist/</guid><description>Photo by Sakshi Shail on Unsplash
Introduction Many of us are familiar with Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s famous words &amp;ldquo;God is dead, and we have killed him&amp;rdquo;, meaning that following the European period known as the Enlightenment, rational and scientific thinking had essentially uprooted the need to believe in the words brought by the Prophets. However, he and the Europeans were quite late to the party. If we go back more than two and a half millennia we will find that a different type of Enlightenment also had the effect of killing the notion of God.</description></item><item><title>Vinaya Schools Network Diagram</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/vinaya-school-connections/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 20:44:41 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/vinaya-school-connections/</guid><description>This interactive visualization maps the historical development of Buddhist monastic lineages from their original unity to the surviving traditions that guide contemporary Buddhist communities worldwide.
&lt;!DOCTYPE html> Buddhist Vinaya Schools Network Buddhist Vinaya Schools Network Visualisation of Early Buddhist School Development
Physics Simulation Show Labels Layout Hierarchical Force-directed School Classifications Pre-sectarian Buddhism Mahāsāṃghika Branch Sthavira Branch Sarvāstivāda Sub-schools Vibhajyavāda Sub-schools Pudgalavāda Sub-schools Other markers Surviving Vinaya Lineages (Mūlasarvāstivāda, Dharmaguptaka, Theravāda) Cross-lineage Connections (Alternative origins/absorption) Note: This diagram represents a simplified view of Buddhist school development.</description></item><item><title>Attached To This Life | ཚེ་འདིར་ཞེན་པའི་ཚོར་སྣང།</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/attached-to-this-life/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/attached-to-this-life/</guid><description>Photo by Rohan Aggarwal on Unsplash
Preface This poem was written during the teaching of Nyingtik Yabshi in May 2024. It is a reflection on attachment to the concerns of this life (ཚེ་འདི་), a fundamental obstacle on the Buddhist path.
In the Kadampa tradition, it is said that if one is attached to this life, one is not a true Dharma practitioner. This poem explores the various ways this attachment manifests—in our relationships with wealth, comfort, reputation, praise, and influence—and how these attachments become obstacles to genuine practice.</description></item><item><title>Reflections on Going Forth | རབ་བྱུང་ཞིག་གི་བསམ་གཞིགས།</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/poem-on-going-forth/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 13:44:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/poem-on-going-forth/</guid><description>Having decided to embark on the spiritual path, Siddhartha cuts his hair, removes his royal garments, and puts on rag robes. Illustration from Life of the Buddha, Burmese Edition, via The Jade Turtle Records.
Preface This poem was written during my second Traditional Rain Retreat. It is a reflection meant to generate the mind of &amp;ldquo;renunciation&amp;rdquo;, although the correct word to convey the meaning of the sanskrit words niḥsaraṇa or niryāṇa would be &amp;ldquo;emergence&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;going forth&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>The 37 Practices of a Bodhisattva's Outline</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/outline-37-bodhisattva-practices/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 17:13:41 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/outline-37-bodhisattva-practices/</guid><description>Given this text has been translated by enough people 1 2 3, I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to make yet another translation. However, while studying a Tibetan commentary from འཇིགས་མེད་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དཔལ་བཟང་། (Jigme Tsultrim Palzang), I came accross an interesting outline that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen before. It really helped me to understand the root text better, so I&amp;rsquo;m sharing the translation I made of this outline.
The outline Each number in parentheses indicates the corresponding practice with a total of 37.</description></item><item><title>Redefining Tibetan Buddhism</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/redefining-tibetan-buddhism/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 11:19:49 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/redefining-tibetan-buddhism/</guid><description>The Bodhisattva Avalokiteshvara in the Form of Shadakshari Lokeshvara: Folio from a manuscript of the Ashtasahasrika Prajnaparamita, courtesy of the Met Museum.
Introduction Tibetan Buddhism has captivated spiritual seekers with its unique expressions, vibrant rituals, and distinctive cultural elements. However, looking beneath the surface reveals a profound truth: Tibetan Buddhism is essentially an exquisite cultural adaptation of the timeless essence of Indian Mahayana Buddhism. This article explores the shared origins, core teachings, and fundamental inseparability of Tibetan Buddhism and Indian Mahayana Buddhism, highlighting the transformative influence of Indian masters and demonstrating that what we call &amp;ldquo;Tibetan Buddhism&amp;rdquo; is more accurately understood as Indian Mahayana Buddhism expressed through a Tibetan cultural lens.</description></item><item><title>About Middle Way Musings</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2023 10:08:13 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/about/</guid><description>Hi, welcome I am a Western European Buddhist monk currently residing in a monastery in Northern India. This blog serves as my outlet to share reflections, insights, and observations through the lens of the Madhyamaka school of Buddhist philosophy.
My Journey My path to monasticism wasn&amp;rsquo;t straightforward. With a background in science and technology, I spent over a decade founding and volunteering with organisations focused on social issues. My career was thriving - I had progressed rapidly through university and professional life, achieved considerable success, and experienced much of what the world offers.</description></item><item><title>Welcome to Middle Way Musings</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/welcome-to-middle-way-musings/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 13:22:52 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/welcome-to-middle-way-musings/</guid><description>Photo by Thien Dang on Unsplash
Today marks the beginning of a new journey. After years of contemplation, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally created this space to share my thoughts as I navigate the path of Buddhist study and practice.
Why &amp;ldquo;Middle Way Musings&amp;rdquo;? The name of this blog reflects both my philosophical orientation and my approach to writing. In the Madhyamaka tradition, the &amp;ldquo;Middle Way&amp;rdquo; refers not simply to moderation, but to a profound philosophical position that avoids the extremes of eternalism and nihilism—neither asserting that phenomena inherently exist nor claiming they are utterly non-existent.</description></item></channel></rss>