<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Madhyamaka on Middle Way Musings</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/tags/madhyamaka/</link><description>Recent content in Madhyamaka on Middle Way Musings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 11:33:18 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://middlewaymusings.com/tags/madhyamaka/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Does God Exist?</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/does-god-exist/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2024 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/does-god-exist/</guid><description>Photo by Sakshi Shail on Unsplash
Introduction Many of us are familiar with Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s famous words &amp;ldquo;God is dead, and we have killed him&amp;rdquo;, meaning that following the European period known as the Enlightenment, rational and scientific thinking had essentially uprooted the need to believe in the words brought by the Prophets. However, he and the Europeans were quite late to the party. If we go back more than two and a half millennia we will find that a different type of Enlightenment also had the effect of killing the notion of God.</description></item><item><title>Is the Big Bang Theory Wrong?</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/is-the-big-bang-theory-wrong/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 11:33:18 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/is-the-big-bang-theory-wrong/</guid><description>Photo by James Webb Telescope
In recent years, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) has unveiled discoveries that have shaken the foundations of our cosmic understanding. Among its most startling findings are fully formed, massive galaxies dating back to just 300-500 million years after the supposed Big Bang—galaxies that, according to conventional Big Bang cosmology, simply shouldn&amp;rsquo;t exist yet. These ancient galaxies appear too large, too mature, and too numerous for the standard timeline of cosmic evolution.</description></item></channel></rss>