<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Mahayana on Middle Way Musings</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.github.io/tags/mahayana/</link><description>Recent content in Mahayana on Middle Way Musings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 17:13:41 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://middlewaymusings.github.io/tags/mahayana/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Secret of Tibetan Buddhism</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.github.io/posts/the-secret-of-tibetan-buddhism/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 11:19:49 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.github.io/posts/the-secret-of-tibetan-buddhism/</guid><description>The Bodhisattva Avalokiteshvara in the Form of Shadakshari Lokeshvara: Folio from a manuscript of the Ashtasahasrika Prajnaparamita, courtesy of the Met Museum.
Introduction Tibetan Buddhism has captivated spiritual seekers with its unique expressions, vibrant rituals, and distinctive cultural elements. However, peering beneath the surface, we discover a profound truth: Tibetan Buddhism is essentially an exquisite wrapping around the timeless essence of Indian Mahayana Buddhism. In this article, we will delve into the shared origins, core teachings, and fundamental unity of Tibetan Buddhism and Indian Mahayana Buddhism, highlighting the transformative influence of Indian masters and emphasizing that the notion of a separate &amp;ldquo;Tibetan&amp;rdquo; Buddhism is merely a different guise for the radiant splendor of Indian Buddhism.</description></item><item><title>The 37 Practices of a Bodhisattva's Outline</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.github.io/posts/outline-37-bodhisattva-practices/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 17:13:41 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.github.io/posts/outline-37-bodhisattva-practices/</guid><description>Given this text has been translated by enough people 1 2 3, I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to make yet another translation. However, while studying a Tibetan commentary from འཇིགས་མེད་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དཔལ་བཟང་། (Jigme Tsultrim Palzang), I came accross an interesting outline that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen before. It really helped me to understand the root text better, so I&amp;rsquo;m sharing the translation I made of this outline.
The outline Each number in parentheses indicates the corresponding practice with a total of 37.</description></item></channel></rss>