<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tibetan on Middle Way Musings</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/tags/tibetan/</link><description>Recent content in Tibetan on Middle Way Musings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 10:30:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://middlewaymusings.com/tags/tibetan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Redefining Tibetan Buddhism</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/redefining-tibetan-buddhism/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 11:19:49 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/redefining-tibetan-buddhism/</guid><description>The Bodhisattva Avalokiteshvara in the Form of Shadakshari Lokeshvara: Folio from a manuscript of the Ashtasahasrika Prajnaparamita, courtesy of the Met Museum.
Introduction Tibetan Buddhism has captivated spiritual seekers with its unique expressions, vibrant rituals, and distinctive cultural elements. However, looking beneath the surface reveals a profound truth: Tibetan Buddhism is essentially an exquisite cultural adaptation of the timeless essence of Indian Mahayana Buddhism. This article explores the shared origins, core teachings, and fundamental inseparability of Tibetan Buddhism and Indian Mahayana Buddhism, highlighting the transformative influence of Indian masters and demonstrating that what we call &amp;ldquo;Tibetan Buddhism&amp;rdquo; is more accurately understood as Indian Mahayana Buddhism expressed through a Tibetan cultural lens.</description></item><item><title>Attached To This Life | ཚེ་འདིར་ཞེན་པའི་ཚོར་སྣང།</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/attached-to-this-life/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 10:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/attached-to-this-life/</guid><description>Photo by Rohan Aggarwal on Unsplash
Preface This poem was written during the teaching of Nyingtik Yabshi in May 2024. It is a reflection on attachment to the concerns of this life (ཚེ་འདི་), a fundamental obstacle on the Buddhist path.
In the Kadampa tradition, it is said that if one is attached to this life, one is not a true Dharma practitioner. This poem explores the various ways this attachment manifests—in our relationships with wealth, comfort, reputation, praise, and influence—and how these attachments become obstacles to genuine practice.</description></item><item><title>Reflections on Going Forth | རབ་བྱུང་ཞིག་གི་བསམ་གཞིགས།</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/poem-on-going-forth/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 13:44:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/poem-on-going-forth/</guid><description>Having decided to embark on the spiritual path, Siddhartha cuts his hair, removes his royal garments, and puts on rag robes. Illustration from Life of the Buddha, Burmese Edition, via The Jade Turtle Records.
Preface This poem was written during my second Traditional Rain Retreat. It is a reflection meant to generate the mind of &amp;ldquo;renunciation&amp;rdquo;, although the correct word to convey the meaning of the sanskrit words niḥsaraṇa or niryāṇa would be &amp;ldquo;emergence&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;going forth&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>The 37 Practices of a Bodhisattva's Outline</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/outline-37-bodhisattva-practices/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 17:13:41 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/outline-37-bodhisattva-practices/</guid><description>Given this text has been translated by enough people 1 2 3, I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to make yet another translation. However, while studying a Tibetan commentary from འཇིགས་མེད་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དཔལ་བཟང་། (Jigme Tsultrim Palzang), I came accross an interesting outline that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen before. It really helped me to understand the root text better, so I&amp;rsquo;m sharing the translation I made of this outline.
The outline Each number in parentheses indicates the corresponding practice with a total of 37.</description></item></channel></rss>