<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Vinaya on Middle Way Musings</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/tags/vinaya/</link><description>Recent content in Vinaya on Middle Way Musings</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 16:00:49 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://middlewaymusings.com/tags/vinaya/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>There Are No Mahayana Monasteries</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/there-are-no-mahayana-monasteries/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 16:00:49 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/there-are-no-mahayana-monasteries/</guid><description>Photo by Raju Kumar on Unsplash
Introduction It has become all too common these days to refer to Buddhist monasteries (by which I mean established monastic communities with sufficient residents to maintain traditional Vinaya observance) by their cultural flair or the doctrinal views they follow. We may call some monasteries &amp;ldquo;Tibetan&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;Zen&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Theravāda&amp;rdquo;, or even &amp;ldquo;Mahāyāna&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Hīnayāna&amp;rdquo; (i.e. Śrāvakayāna). While it may seem to make sense, these labels create unnecessary barriers between monastics who are actually much closer spiritual siblings than it may appear.</description></item><item><title>Vinaya Schools Network Diagram</title><link>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/vinaya-school-connections/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 20:44:41 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://middlewaymusings.com/posts/vinaya-school-connections/</guid><description>This interactive visualization maps the historical development of Buddhist monastic lineages from their original unity to the surviving traditions that guide contemporary Buddhist communities worldwide.
&lt;!DOCTYPE html> Buddhist Vinaya Schools Network Buddhist Vinaya Schools Network Visualisation of Early Buddhist School Development
Physics Simulation Show Labels Layout Hierarchical Force-directed School Classifications Pre-sectarian Buddhism Mahāsāṃghika Branch Sthavira Branch Sarvāstivāda Sub-schools Vibhajyavāda Sub-schools Pudgalavāda Sub-schools Other markers Surviving Vinaya Lineages (Mūlasarvāstivāda, Dharmaguptaka, Theravāda) Cross-lineage Connections (Alternative origins/absorption) Note: This diagram represents a simplified view of Buddhist school development.</description></item></channel></rss>